<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse, betvveene Vpright the shoomaker and Master Pattent, the smith Both meeting on the horse exchange in Smithfield, on the 20. day of Aprill 1639. Ne sutor vltra crepidam. By T.J.</title>
            <author>T. J., fl. 1640.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 24 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03960</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14066</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119111</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854318</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854318</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19732</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03960)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19732)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1549:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse, betvveene Vpright the shoomaker and Master Pattent, the smith Both meeting on the horse exchange in Smithfield, on the 20. day of Aprill 1639. Ne sutor vltra crepidam. By T.J.</title>
                  <author>T. J., fl. 1640.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B. Alsop, and T. F[awcet] for Francis Groves dwelling on Snow-Hill neare the Sarazens Head,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1640.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dialogues, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19732:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Diſcourſe, Betweene VPRIGHT the SHOOMAKER AND MASTER PATTENT, the SMITH.</p>
            <p>Both meeting on the Horſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change in <hi>Smithfield,</hi> on the 20. day of <hi>Aprill.</hi> 1639.</p>
            <q>Ne Sutor vltra Crepidam. By T. J.</q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>two men in conversation</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by B. ALIOP, and T. F. for <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Groves</hi> dwelling on Snow-Hill meare the <hi>Sarazens</hi> Head. 1640.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:19732:2"/>
            <head>VPRIGHT. AND PATTENT.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pattent</speaker>
               <p>VVHether in ſuch haſt Mr. <hi>Upright;</hi> you looke as if you did not know me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Upright.</speaker>
               <p>I doe indéed Sir, yet I am perſwaded I have ſéene you; and now I thinke ont, twas at the Seſſions houſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pattent.</speaker>
               <p>Right Sir, my name is <hi>Pattent;</hi> I endited <hi>Mr. Chambergaine</hi> for receiving of Inmates:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Upright.</speaker>
               <p>I perfectly remember you good <hi>Mr. Pattent;</hi> how go s trading with you now, I am afraid wée ſhall have a dead time on't, you have little to doe I thinke; when <hi>Summer</hi> comes Pattents grow out of date.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:19732:2"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>You are in the right ſir, and which is worſs, the City had rather goe wet ſhod then have them brought vp againe</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Up.</speaker>
               <p>Say you ſo, troth I cannot much blame them, for to ſay truth, you have not made them ſet viceable for the Common wealth, you have onely a reſpect to your private gaine Maſter Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, you got ſweetly for the time they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>By your ſavour Maſter <hi>Vpright,</hi> now you talke of deceit in Trading, I muſt tell you your owne too: did you never vent Calves Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for Neate, and oftentimes for Spaniſh to ſome ignorant Cuſtomers: nay now you tell me of vnſerviceable ware, how many of the Kings Subiects have you put in the ſtockes without au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority not vagranto and Beggars, but Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. Marchants, Citizens, with their wives and aughters.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vpright.</speaker>
               <p>I vnderſtand your wit: you meane that I have made their ſhooes too little for them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>Yes ſir,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vp.</speaker>
               <p>They had better be in the Shoomakers ſtacks, then be ſo gauled by Pattents as they have béene.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>I doe not thinke but you have drankt your <pb facs="tcp:19732:3"/>Mornings draught in Wormewood Béere Mr. <hi>Vpright.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vpright.</speaker>
               <p>Why?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>You fall ſo bitter vpon me:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vp.</speaker>
               <p>I ſhall be bitterer ere we part Maſter Pattent.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>Doe thy worſt Shoomaker.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vpright.</speaker>
               <p>No no no, not the worſt neither: The beſt I have to tell you will make you made enough, doe you remember when you were Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable Maſter
<hi>Pattent,</hi> when you tooke me in your watch on Criſpine and Criſpianus Night, and carried me to the Counter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>Ha ha ha, yes I doe, I doe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vp.</speaker>
               <p>Doe you laugh at it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>Yes ſaith, I remember you went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond your Laſt then.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vpright:</speaker>
               <p>I remember thou wer't the troubleſom'ſt ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rannicall Conſtable that ever knock'd down ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity with a painted ſtaffer Thou would'ſt have a finger in every mans buſineſſe, thy very name was hatefull, if they did but heare of <hi>Pattent</hi> they were danted, thou haſt had a pernicious wit, or elſe thou could'ſt never overcome Scriveners and Brokers, they have curſt thée ſufficiently, the low Country Butter-boxes wiſhed tenne <pb facs="tcp:19732:3"/>hundred thouſand funne of Devill take thee, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe they were forced to waight for Butter till you brought the tranſporters to compoſition: And what had your Loggerhead to doe with Mr. <hi>Logwood</hi> the <hi>Dyer;</hi> thou wilt vndertake to teach people to dye well, and thy ſelfe could'ſt never live well.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pattent.</speaker>
               <p>Very good.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vp.</speaker>
               <p>Not very had ſir, tis you I am talking off, doe you heare
<hi>Pattent,</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Marchant <hi>Don tobacco</hi> vowes a revenge vpon thée, and I much feare he will take thy life: for he ſayes he will ſend his two Factors, <hi>Verinus</hi> and
<hi>Mandun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> to ſtifle thée.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pattent.</speaker>
               <p>The devill he will, they are from him already man he hath put them to boord in blind Ale-houſes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Upright.</speaker>
               <p>No matter, ther's more wayes to kill a Dog then hanging of him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pattent.</speaker>
               <p>A Dogge you Dunſtable.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vpright.</speaker>
               <p>Yes you payer Kite, and now I talke of hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, there could not be ſo much as the hangmans office to ſell but Tyburne, and the reſt of his kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred muſt allow you a pention for it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pattent.</speaker>
               <p>So, ſo, ſo, can Saint <hi>Hugh</hi> and his bones protect you to talke thus liberally Shooma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:19732:4"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Upright.</speaker>
               <p>Oh yes, yes, yes, thou giv'ſt me au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, I know I may talke fréely by patent my friend:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pattent.</speaker>
               <p>It was Maſter <hi>Patent.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vpright.</speaker>
               <p>I that was when you traded in ſhéepskins and Lambskins oh thou wer't a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Woolfe in Lambskinne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pattent.</speaker>
               <p>You will anſwer all this, will you not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vpright.</speaker>
               <p>No, I ſcorne it, I beléeve I have ſpoke more then thou canſt anſwer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pattent.</speaker>
               <p>But heark ye goodman Shoomaker.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vpright.</speaker>
               <p>Goodman Shoomaker, I deny and defie the title. I am a Gentleman, my gentility is of Antiquity, thou art an Vpſtart; Shooes were made when thy villanous Pattenis were not thought on.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>Well I may chauce ſhortly brew a little Worme wood for you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vp.</speaker>
               <p>Brew ſay you, you have brewed for vs already I thanke you, all the Gentlemen Cord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayners in St. Martins doe wiſh but to have the browning of thée for abuſing the Brewers: which hath made them abuſe vs and ſend vs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanted ſmall Beere in ſtead of ſtrong, before you had a hand in the Brewhouſe we could have old <hi>Engliſh</hi> beere would makes all madde before Munday noone, now tis ſo ſmall we can ſcarce <pb facs="tcp:19732:4"/>get drunke by <hi>Tueſday</hi> Night, a whole tunne of our béere will ſcarce for a <hi>Dutchman:</hi> this you have done good Maſter Pattent.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>Shall I be blam'd for this, I thinke I did the Common wealth a great deale of good to kéepe it ſober.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vp.</speaker>
               <p>I thou art a neceſſary member for in kée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of them from being drunke, thou mak'ſt them mad, as I run a Shoomaker and frée of the Cordwainers, every prentize, I had came home ſober laſt
<hi>Shrovetueſday</hi> night: It was not ſo I am ſure when I was a Lad:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>Hay, hay?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vp.</speaker>
               <p>Yes and ſtraw to, you put me well in mind on't, the horſes that had béen well bred and pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per'd in the Country, and had their allowance of hay fréely, and lay at racke and manger, eat what they would; now they are ſrinted: how many pound of hay is there in a Load Mr. Pattent.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>I cannot tell?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Up.</speaker>
               <p>Wée muſt buy hay for our horſes as we buy ſigs by the pound doe you beléeve when you waighed Hay that Iuſtice held the States.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>I ſée you will have Licenſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vp.</speaker>
               <p>Not from you Iack ſtraw, vnleſſe you were in office againe:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>Iacke ſtraw?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vp.</speaker>
               <p>I prethée anſwer me to one queſtion and <pb facs="tcp:19732:5"/>he juſt with me to a ſtrawes breadth?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>Declare your wit?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Up.</speaker>
               <p>How many ounces of ſtraw goes to the littering of a Mad man a yeare in <hi>Bedlam.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis a madde queſtion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Up.</speaker>
               <p>I that's true, I know who I ſpeake to.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pattent.</speaker>
               <p>Why doe you count me for a Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vp.</speaker>
               <p>No for a wiſe man: and a man that hath had experience ith miſtery, this is no queſtion for a Mad-man to anſwer:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>It ſéemes your converſation is altogether with wiſe acres: was it not you that asked the ſilly queſtion once; whether Red-herrings came out of the red Sea or no.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vp.</speaker>
               <p>No but it was you that made men pay as deare for them, as if they came from thence, I wonder you had nothing to doe with dainty blote herring, blote, blote, or dryed Sprats; I beléeve you had ſomething to doe with Gudgeons, though thy ſelfe art as miſerable now as poore
<hi>Iohn</hi> was<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is it not you that one Lent endited a poore man of Felony for frying of Bacon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pattent.</speaker>
               <p>Of Fellony?</p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:19732:5"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vpright.</speaker>
               <p>Yes of Fellony, and you would néeds juſtifie it with an Act of Parliament, which when one looked on it which had better eyes, it was not frying of Bacon, but flering a Beacon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pattent.</speaker>
               <p>Ha ha ha.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vpright.</speaker>
               <p>Doeſt thou laugh at thy owne igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, doe you heare
<hi>Patent,</hi> did I never know you a Dunghill Raker.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>I a Dunghill raker, ye Pantoffle.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vp.</speaker>
               <p>I cry you mercy Sir, you did onely rake them that raked Dunghills, looke too't, for there is an army comming againſt thee, whoſe wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons are ſtrong yron hookes; the Captaine of them is <hi>Tattardemalion Tagragg:</hi> thoſe that be vnder his command I ſhall nominate to thee.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Britch bottome out,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ralph Parch and ſtitch,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Will worke and faſt,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Hadge Leather Scrap,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sam Scrape and take,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Daniell Dunghill Worke.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>And a great many more out of my memory at this time that have made vp a ragged Regiment and vow no more to be obedient to thy authority Moreover the Hop Marchants have an intent. on to marry all the female Bonelace makers, and get Children to fortifie themſelves againſt thee <pb facs="tcp:19732:6"/>they ſay if thou doſt but come amongſt their hops againe, they will ſcarce leave thee a leg to hop a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way vpon, and the Bonelace makers have taken ſuch ſpirit againſt thée, that in ſtead of Bone-Lace thou ſhalt returne with laced bones, and take my word <hi>Pattent,</hi> thou hadſt better be in the middle of <hi>Engliſh</hi> pikes, then amongſt their <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> néedles.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>Doe you hold any confedraſe with this lawleſſe faction Mr.
<hi>Vpright</hi> that you can ſo well tell the manner of the revenges they will execute vpon me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vp.</speaker>
               <p>I promiſe thée I doe not thinke but they will burne thee when all comes to all, and ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s an end of <hi>Pattent.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>It muſt be ſome of your female Bone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace makers then, I care not a button for the reſt of the Rebellions.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Up.</speaker>
               <p>Don't you care a button? Maſter <hi>Panyer</hi> in <hi>Hoope Ally</hi> will make you care a button, why thou Iack in a boxe, could'ſt not thou be content to gaine Authority omongſt the Buttonmakers of
<hi>Amſterdam,</hi> where the ſiſterhood might have payed thee tribute; beſides Buttons for thy bréeches.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>Yes when their breeches make buttons, have I lived after that rate to goe ſecured among Preciſians you vagrants.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:19732:6"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vp.</speaker>
               <p>Among Preciſians you puppie, what néed you confine your ſelfe to one Sect when there is ſo much diviſion amongſt them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>That's all one, they hold the greateſt ſway who care no more for knocking a mans braines out in zeale, or for the good of the common cauſe: then I for philiping a flie to death, I would not be within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> juriſdiction of new <hi>England</hi> for a million.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vp.</speaker>
               <p>Nay I thinke thou hadſt better be in the great <hi>Maguls</hi> Countrie:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>Or have béen Page to Sir <hi>John Mande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill,</hi> I ſhould hope to returne with more ſecurity.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vp.</speaker>
               <p>Well, but now we have béen in <hi>Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, New England,</hi> and <hi>Magoll;</hi> let vs returne to old <hi>England</hi> againe, where there is many ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men will welcome you home, one Mr.
<hi>Cipres.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>Oh the Hathand maker.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Up.</speaker>
               <p>Then theres another one Mr <hi>Kitling.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>A fiddle ſtring maker?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vp.</speaker>
               <p>Maſter <hi>Clay:</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>A Tobackopipe maker?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vp.</speaker>
               <p>Maſter <hi>Glaſſe Eyes.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>A Spectacle maker?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>vp.</speaker>
               <p>Maſter <hi>Curry:</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>A Combmaker?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vp.</speaker>
               <p>Doe you heare Pattent cannot you dance all trades, how many Halls have you béen free of:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>Whats that to thée?</p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:19732:7"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>V.</speaker>
               <p>That is a queſtion all men aske when they are aſhamed to give an anſwer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>Aſhamed?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>vp.</speaker>
               <p>Did I ſay thou wert aſhamed:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>'Twas your pleaſure?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>vp.</speaker>
               <p>Give me thy hand I am ſorry for it, I cry thée mercy I tooke my markes amiſſe: Ile give thee thy due for that efaith I thinke thou wert e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhameleſſe, have I hit the Naile on the head now Smith, are you pleaſed:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>You have ſpoken all?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>vp.</speaker>
               <p>Not all, but I am drawing to an end?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>Would thou hadſt ſpoke thy laſt once?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>vp.</speaker>
               <p>I ſhall vexe thy ſoule firſt Sirrah, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe thou canſt come off with good Language, thou wilt ſuffer many Deaths in one, the Hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band maker will choake thée or ſtrangle thée with
<hi>Cipres,</hi> the Gut ſtring maker will make ſtrings of thy Guts which will cozen the Fid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers moſt abhominably, for they will never ſtand in Tune, the Tobackopipe makers, Spectacle makers, and Combe makers, will compound with the Dicemakers for thy bones to make falce Dice with, and that's a way to make thée as miſchievous in thy Death as thou wer't in thy lifetime, and if thy Bones prove ſo deceitfull, we may very well turne the tother end of an old Proverb, what was bred in thy fleſh will never out of thy bones.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:19732:7"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>I have heard you, and doubt not the worſt their mallice aymes to inflict vpon me, I have ere this my tragedy he brought to paſſe, contriv'd a meanes to worke revenge on them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vp.</speaker>
               <p>Declare, I ſhall be glad to heare it, I always had an itching deſire to miſchiefe as well as thou:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>Thus then, I will bring up a faſhion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſome of our temporiſing gallants to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the wearing of hatbonds, we will have all our fiddle ſtrings from <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Venice,</hi> and as I am a Smith. I have a conceit to make yron to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backo pipes and ſteele Combes, and our old men when they once grow dimme ſighted, ſhall have their writings read to them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vp.</speaker>
               <p>I this is prety well, but not in your power to perfect, this is a harder project vpon them, then the firſt you had, it will be a hard matter to draw the humours of the whole Kingdome to theſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhions: beſides your yron worke will doe no good, for we have many phantaſlike Company kéepers that onely take Tobacko to breake the pipes, and ſhall we be beholding to other Nations for fiddle ſtrings or combe our heads with Horſe Combes. Beſides ther's a ſtrange conceit indéed that all old men ſhould have their writings read to them, 'tis enough to vndoe halfe the old men in the Kingdome, their Miſtreſſes ſhall not ſend to them letters of commendation, or places of new <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19732:8"/>mieting, but they muſt be enforc'd to have their wives to read them, and what inconveniency that would bring, doe but judge: No no, this will not doe Mr. <hi>Pattent,</hi> I am a little in haſt, I thinke it be dinner time, I will onely give you one item more and then i'le leave you to your owne direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, were you never acquainted with one Mr. <hi>Fortune.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, yes, a Horner.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vp.</speaker>
               <p>Ware horns, take héed of him are you marid.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>What of that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vp.</speaker>
               <p>Take héed of him, that is all; I ſpeake as a Friend.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pattent.</speaker>
               <p>Friendly councell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vpright.</speaker>
               <p>It is ſo, then doe not you know Mr. Kill Cow.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>Yes the Butcher.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vp.</speaker>
               <p>The very ſame, he hath a great many friends abroad, ſo hath
<hi>Ball</hi> his Dog, be ſure you goe not through field lane, Newgate market, Butcher row, St. <hi>Nicholas</hi> ſhambles, Eaſt Cheape, or
<hi>Southwark,</hi> there is wait laid for thée in all theſe places, and if they meet thee thou wilt be ſtucke fuller of Skuers then a Surloyne of roaſt beefe at <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> is ſtucke with Roſemary: And by all meanes come not neare the Beare garden for wares and Dogs are friends and all agrée, on thée to act a bloody Tragedy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>Well ſirrah, you are a vailing fellow, I'le talke no more to you?</p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:19732:8"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vp.</speaker>
               <p>One cold word more good Maſter <hi>Pattent.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>But ſirrah why doth theſe things trouble you ſo much?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Up.</speaker>
               <p>I tell thée my name is <hi>vpright,</hi> my nature is like vnto my name, and I defie ſuch juggling in a Common-wealth, it makes my honeſt coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymen beg, in a land of plentie; I have ſomthing to ſay to you (now I conſider <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> is ſo neare) concerning Cards, what new game have you ſet a foot, that the knave of Dyamonds doth cozen the king of Hearts and all his Subjects to the very Ace, y' are a ſure Card ſirrah, when <hi>Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent</hi> deales, all the reſt doe but hold Cards.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>Why not, why I tell thée I will cozen my Father at Cards.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vp.</speaker>
               <p>Prethée doe not ſweare ile belée ve thée, the Father quoth he, I the Father of thy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try — you are going now, you doe not love to heare of your faults, I haue onely one thing more to ſay to thée, &amp; then fire or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iakes conſume thée.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>I thanke you ſir, ſpit out your ſpléene, what is your next venome?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vp.</speaker>
               <p>No venome vpon my credit, now I have laid open thy ſoule inſide, I will give thée a purge that is with Soape:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>With Soape?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vp.</speaker>
               <p>With Sope, I with Sope, that was a purge déere enough as you order'd it, all the good Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wifes <pb facs="tcp:19732:9"/>in <hi>London,</hi> and thoſe that take a pride in cleane linnen, have an intention to waſh thée cléere from all thy former villanies; but I am a fraid they will doe no good vpon thee, they will be enforced at laſt to hang thee vp for the ſigne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Labour in vaine, which is the end I bequeath thée too, and though I am no Barbar good Mr. <hi>Pattent,</hi> I muſt leave you ith ſuds at this time, for I have talk'd my ſelfe weary, my ſhop Iournimen and prentiſes expect me, if you have any thing to ſay to me, you know St. <hi>Martins,</hi> I will not change my houſe now the world is in hope of reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. So good even ſwéet Maſter
<hi>Pattent.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
               <p>Farewell ſir?</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>And though theſe things I can no longer thrive by,</l>
                  <l>Hang him that wants, who hath all Trades to live by.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And ſo Maſter <hi>Patten,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Pray learne this martin,</l>
                  <l>The ſeat which you ſat in,</l>
                  <l>In your furs and your ſatten</l>
                  <l>Muſt now be forſaken,</l>
                  <l>Your knavery is taken,</l>
                  <l>And toth Devill removed.</l>
                  <l>Your dearly beloved.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19732:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
